Gershom Bulkeley manuscripts
Hartford Medical Society
Gershom Bulkeley manuscripts
1636-1713
Bulkeley, Gershom, 1636-1713
2018-01
4 24
Hartford Medical Society
This collection primarily contains Bulkeley's laboratory notebooks which detail his alchemical experiments and his transcriptions of contemporary scientific works. The manuscripts are handwritten and do not necessarily follow a logical linear sequence.
Restrictions
These items are extremely fragile. They may be viewed by researchers following strict archival procedures.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Gurdon W. Russell, founding member of Hartford Medical Society.
Biography
The following biographical information is taken from: Steiner, W. R. (1904). The Reverend Gershom Bulkeley of Connecticut, an Eminent Clerical Physician. *Medical library and historical journal*, 2(2), 91.
Gershom Bulkeley was an eminent Clerical Physician. He preached in a church in Wethersfield, Connecticut between 1666-1667 when he resigned by reason of weakness of his voice. After his retirement, he moved to Glastonbury and maintained a large medical practice. His patients came from a wide territory and included some of the best families of the state. With all these patients, many of whom he treated before 1686, it seems strange that he was not licensed to practice medicine until October 14 of that year. His library is now much scattered and destroyed. Besides the group of about 34 [sic] volumes owned by the Hartford Medical Society, some are in the possession of Trinity College. His manuscripts show that he was in the habit of making abstracts of important articles and books that he did not own. He was also constantly recording prescriptions and remedies said to be effectual by members of his profession or the laity. His knowledge of chemistry was most profound, and his laboratory was well stocked with apparatus and chemicals. He was a master of several languages, among which were Greek, Latin and Dutch. Besides theology and medicine, he was skilled in the knowledge of law and was a politician in the noblest sense of the word. His pamphlets, "The People's Right to Election", and "Will and Doom" shoed his Tory tendencies.
Scope and Content of Collection
24 handwritten manuscripts. See container listing for details.
Arrangement
No formal arrangement. Items are described in the container list.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Bulkeley, Gershom, 1636-1713; Russell, Gurdon Wadsworth, 1815-1909; Alchemy; History of Medicine, 17th Century; manuscripts (documents)
- Inventory
  - Notes on Alsted, Johannes Henricus 01, 1655-1713; Notes on Alsted, Johannes Henricus. The scientific parts of his "Encyclopedia", p. 1-475. In the back of the volume is a treatise on "The Office of [Justice of] the Peace. P. 1-88. n.d. Vellum binding, 17 cm. (Item 1)
  - Treat, Richard, 1740-1755; Treat, Richard. [Son-in-law or grandson of Gershom Bulkeley?] Varied content. Front and back contains a medical account book, 1740-1755. Middle of volume contains extracts of Mr. Charles Morten’s System of Philosophy (Compendium Physicae) [This work available from the Colonial Society of Massachusetts.] Some Greek notes. 20 cm. wide. No binding. Back loose, poor condition. (Item 2)
  - Varied content 01, 1657-1729; Varied content. Medical and chemical notes. Contents: Discovery of the general effects of wines, p. 21 | Yarranton, Andrew, "On Clover", p. 36 – Signed "G.B., Dec. 5, 1662", p. 44 | List of catalogue of some usefull and universalle things, p. 45 | Notes on a volume [title obscure] by Valentini, Michael Bernhardus, 1657-1729, p. 49. Back of book has treatise, "Prolegomena de Arte in Genera." This latter portion is in a different handwriting, which may be that of his father, (Peter Bulkeley, the Elder.) n.d. 125 p.[portion unpaged] 28 cm. Vellum binding with hole in front cover. (Item 3)
  - Laboratory book 01, 1679-1713; Laboratory Book (?) Contains also excerpts from a chemical volume 1679. Also notes on other matters, especially agriculture. Unpaged. 10 cm wide. Cloth binding with board covers. (Item 4)
  - Laboratory book 02, 1703-1706; Laboratory book of chemical experiments. Contains also some excerpts from chemical books. 1703-1706. 244 p., 44p. 15 cm. Cloth binding with undistinguishable printing in gold on the back. Binding and several pages loose. (Item 5)
  - Recipe book, 1655-1713; Recipe book [medicinal]. Includes also some medical excerpts. n.d. Unpaged. 19 cm. Cloth binding with board covers. (Item 6)
  - Treatise on Sal Alcoli, 1702-1713; [Treatise on] Sal Alcoli, or some observations concerning the production & nature & qualitys & virtue & excellency & of volatilization of Alcolyes. Also additional material. Sal Alcoli has 6 chapters, p. 1-265. Additional material, p. 265-331. n.d. (p. 265 has date of May 14, 1702). 331 p. 18 cm. Vellum binding with back and ties broken. (Item 7)
  - Sermon and notes, 1661-1662; Sermon, notes and other theosophical notes at both ends. Also contains notes on chemical & medicinal matters. He was very young when portions of this volume were written, 1661-1662(?) Sections written partly in the "short-hand" or "code" so often used by Gershom Bulkeley. Most of the notes are in Latin. v.p. (small section is numbered). 19 cm. wide. Vellum binding in poor condition. Many pages are water stained and torn. Ties broken. (Item 8)
  - Fragment, 1655-1713; Fragment. Excerpts from chemical and medical literature. 68-110 p. 32 cm. Leather binding loose. Pages water stained and torn. In poor condition. (Item 9)
  - Notebooks, 1655-1713; Multiple notebooks tied together with string. (Item 10)
  - Treat, Dorothy, 1721-1721; Treat, Dorothy. [Daughter of Gershom Bulkeley.] Contents unknown, subject matter appears to be medical. Fly leaf reads "Dorothy Treat her booke, 1721". The script looks much like Gershom Bulkeley’s. 379 p. 16 cm. Leather binding, ties broken. (Item 11)
  - Medical account book, 1708-1714; [Medical account book, Apr. 25, 1708 – Mar. 9, 1714]. "Ment. All of accounts in this book are rated as - - cash, except perhaps some few which shall be distinguished if any such shall be". Last three entries have a different handwriting. 29 cm. Vellum binding. Last few pages loose from binding. A large section of the last page has been cut out. (Item 12)
  - Varied content 02, 1655-1713; Varied content. The volume was planned for notes on [Outlines and Beginnings] of "Praedicamentum Substantia", a philosophical-scientific treatise by John Fox, and "taken over" by Gershom Bulkeley for his notes on medical books by Richard Mathew, and Thomas Willis, which are interspersed throughout the entire volume. The back of the volume consists of notes on a [Treatise on] "Transubstantiation" by John Hooper. Contents: Notes on "Praedicamentum Substantia", p. 1-2 | Gershom Bulkeley’s notes on, "Bezoardica", p. 3-9. (obscure) | Notes on "Praedicamentum Substantia", p. 10-11 | Gershom Bulkeley’s Miscellaneous Notes on Chemistry, p. 13-71 | Notes on "Universal Alchymye" by Richard Mathew, p. 72-74 | Gershom Bulkeley’s Chemical Notes, p. 75-116 | Notes on "Observationes quodam experitionalis medicamentum, & ex Schodero, (obscure), p. 117-124; 739-741; 751-754 | Notes on Willis, Thomas, 1622-1675, Pharmacentica Rationalis sive distriba de medicamentorum operationibus in humano corpora. Oxoniae, R. Davis, 1678-79. 2 parts in 1 vol. Pars Prima, p. 125-297; Pars seconda p. 299-498. Date of completing these notes given as Jun. 9, 1692 | Notes on Willis, Thomas, 1622-75. Diatribae duae medico-philosophicae quarum prior agit de fermentation sive de motu intestine particularum in quovis corpora, altera de febrilus sive de motu earundum in sanquini animalium: his accessit dessertatio epistilica de urinis. Ed. Secunda. Londini, T. Roycroft, 1660. 376 p. pp. 499-684; 733-738 (note at foot of p. 738 says that "following chapters are in another book in Quarto") (obscure) | Index to Gershom Bulkeley’s notes, p. 685-718 | Index as planned for "Praedicamentum Substantia", p. 719-729 (G. Bulkeley’s notes interspersed) | P. 731-732 has been cut from the volume | Between p. 741-754 appear Notes on "Transubstantiation" by John Hopper, (in upside-down fashion, working from the back of the book. Notes in Greek. Pages un-numbered. One page cut entirely from these notes.) | 754 pages, n.d. 32 cm. Vellum binding. Contains script other than that of G. Bulkeley, in Latin and Greek. (Item 13)
  - Bulkeley, Peter, 1655-1713; Bulkeley, Peter. [The younger brother of Gershom?] Varied content. Medical and chemical notes. Also many pages of poetry. Gershom Bulkeley has also written in this volume. One section contains the "short-hand" or "code" used frequently by Gershom Bulkeley. Only a portion of the volume is paged. 20 cm. Vellum binding with "cut-out" and pen drawing of a face on front cover. Ties broken. (Item 14)
  - Invoyce of Goods, 1684-1686; The Invoyce of Goods bought of Mr. Thomas Bulkeley, July 3, 1684. Volume also contains other expense accounts interspersed with notes of books on chemistry, 1684-1686? 59 p. 15 cm. Covers lacking. Outside pages torn. (Item 15)
  - Notes on Riverus, Lazarus, 1660-1673; Notes on Riverus, Lazarus, "Praxis medica" Edito ultima. Lugduni, J.A. Huguetan & M.A. Ravaud, 1660. Notes end on p. 313, date Jan. 8, 1673. Remainder of volume has other abstracts. n.d. 30 cm. Leather binding with broken spine and back cover missing. Pages are water stained and some are badly torn. Portions may be lost. (Item 16)
  - Notes on Batavi, 1687-1713; Notes on Batavi... Med. Doctors... Chemica Rationali Collecta.. Apr. 1687. Description and treatment of diseases and medical recipes. 379 p. Incl. table of contents. 15 cm. Vellum binding with ties. (Item 17)
  - Vircow Classierow Espirolarunt, 1672-1713; "Vircow Classierow Espirolarunt." "Collectonae ex Epistola Gorlis," 1672 (1673). 564 pages that appear to be medical pharmacopeia and experiments. 16 cm. Vellum binding with ties. (Item 18)
  - Notes on Alsted, Johannes Henricus 02, 1655-1713; Notes on Alsted, Johannes Henricus. The Salerano School, Encyclopedia of Medicine, p. 1-37 | From the History of the Royal Society of London, p. 38-55 | History of the making of gun powder, p. 56-62 | Sir Will Patty, an apparatus of the history of the common practices of dying, p. 63-88 | Chynicus Rationalis, p. 89 | The expecial Discovery, p. 90-93, followed by 8 chapters of "clynicall observations." (Item 19)
  - Medicinae pro Pauperibus, 1655-1713; N.C. Med. Pro Pauperibus, [Medicine for Poor People]. Whether this volume consists of original work or excerpts is unknown. First seven pages include an alphabetical index. n.d. 16 cm. Covers lacking. Outside pages frayed with some water spots. (Item 20)
  - Goodman Curtis, 1680-1680; The small certificate reads as follows: "Goodman Curtis, These may certify you that I shall pay, or cause to be payed to you, or your assignees, in Wethersfield, on the account of South Hurlbutt, the full sum of three pounds and five shillings in good and merchandisable wheat and Indian corn, in the spring next ensuing this April 12, 1680. Witness my hand, Gershom Bulkeley" (Item 21)
  - Pharmacopea, 1655-1713; Pharmacopea, in Latin. "Notes from, Petri Potery Andegasensis... Consilae Medici Regis... Christianissuri. Pharmacopaea Spagyriea. 189 p., includes index. 18 cm. Leather binding with metal clasp. (Item 22)
  - Medical excerpts, 1655-1713; Medical excerpts from more than one place. Opens from end... two-directional use. 15 cm. Leather cover with cloth spine. (Item 23)
  - The Family Physician, 1696-1713; (not in Gershom’s handwriting). "The Family Physician.. ." by George Hartman, physio-chymist, London, 1696. Chapters 1-24. 96 p., the last few missing. (Item 24)